Guide to the Tristan Klingsor Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Tristan Klingsor papers
1926-1966
GEN MSS 502
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.21
(1 box)
A collection of personal papers, most dating from the end of Klingsor's life, including: letters from Maurice Carême, George-Day, André Ruyters, and Charles Vildrac, among others; a notebook containing lecture notes on Marie Nodier and copied poems; a leaf of a manuscript titled "Isolés at Oubliés", three photographs, and four folders of assorted financial papers.
Klingsor, Tristan, 1874-1966
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Compagnie des Commissaires-Priseurs on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 2001.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
TRISTAN KLINGSOR, 1874-1966
Tristan Klingsor (born Léon Leclère), was a poet, painter and musician, known for his collaborations with Maurice Ravel.
Scope and Contents
This group of material contains a notebook, a holograph page of a work by Klingsor, letters to Klingsor, drafts of letters by Klingsor, financial papers, photographs, and other personal papers.
Authors, French -- 20th Century; Musicians -- France -- 20th Century; Poets, French -- 20th Century; Authors; Musicians; Poets; George-Day; Carême, Maurice, 1899-1978; Klingsor, Tristan, 1874-1966; Menessier-Nodier, Marie, 1811-1893; Ruyters, André; Vildrac, Charles, 1882-1971
- Box and folder list
  - Manuscript page: "Isolés et oubliés", holograph, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Notebook containing lecture notes on Marie Rodier, copied poems, bibliographic lists, and addresses (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Portfolio of notes re: Affaire Leclère contre Allemand, 1962, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Notes: names and addresses (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - "Sonnet pour Monsieur Tristan Klingsor", holograph, by Lydia [Dubourg?], 1962 Mar 11 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Drafts of letters by Klingsor, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Letters to Klingsor from:
    - L'amitié par le livre, 1963 [Dec?] 30 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Carême, Maurice, 1963 Aug 5 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - George-Day, 1963-66 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Houville, Gérard d' [Marie de Régnier], n.d. (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Lacombe, Paul, 1926 Jun 17 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Le Dantec, Yves-Gérard, 1949 Mar 3 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Librairie A. Hatier, 1957 Mar 14 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Ruyters, André (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Vildrac, Charles, 1949 Apr 24 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Various correspondents, ca. 1952-66 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Photographs, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Certificate of the Légion d'honneur, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Voting cards, 1932, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Printed keepsake from the Imagerie Pellerin, ca. 1965 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Financial papers, 1928-66 (Box 1, Folder 21-24)